# RYN ESCARRA-CYPHER

STRATEGIC RESEARCH CONSULTANT

+1 312.622.3656 R.ESCARRACYPHER@GMAIL.COM WWW.RYNESCARRACYPHER.COM

#### SUMMARY

Tenacious, transparent, & thoughtful. I'm an experienced researcher, developer, & strategist who believes in the capacity to create transformative solutions through research & design. I have a strong interest in projects that require both conceptual & analytical thinking. After years in academic research, analytics, & experience design, I have a deep understanding of how attitudes, behaviors, & social contexts shape outcomes.

\*willing to relocate or commit to remote contract work

## SKILLS + PROFICIENCY

Microsoft Suite

Google Suite | Google Analytics

AirTable

Adobe Creative Suite: Photoshop, InDesign, etc.

SPSS

Amazon MTurk

Qualtrics

Inquisit 5/Millisecond

SQL | Sequelize | MongoDB

Express / NodeJS

JavaScript / jQuery

HTML5 / CSS3 | Responsive Design

APIs / CRUD / REST

Python & R for AI / Deep Learning \*active study\*

Constant Contact | Canva

Version Control

Unit Testing

Agile Methodology

Project Management (non-PMP)

Facial Action Coding (FACS)

High EQ

Strong written & verbal communication

Self-motivated, self-started & superb team player

## COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT

VOLUNTEER | Greater Chicago Food Depository | 2008

COACH | One Million Degrees, Chicago | 2018

### **EXPERIENCE**

PT CONSULTANT | Independent Contract | 2018 - PRESENT For- & Not-For-Profit Clientele; Data analytics & visualization. Database design & management, including business & personal financial records, real estate, corporate & individual donations, etc. Development & dissemination of marketing materials for new & existing markets. One-on-one executive leadership assistance & business development strategy.

LAB MANAGER | Emotion & Cognition Laboratory | 2016-2017

Responsible for overall operational elements of laboratory functioning, as representative of PI. Oversees two grants from the NIH (R01) & NSF (SES) & a team of 10-15 key research personnel & assistants. Coordinates multiple projects in a fast-paced, highly professional environment. Implements experimental protocols & writes literature reviews, grant proposals, & manuscripts in conjunction with PI. Designs concept for computer databases to appropriately collect data. Performs complex data analyses using Excel, SPSS. Leads weekly lab meetings to discuss current findings. Responsible for planning all preliminary experiments used to inform the strategic implementation of a 2-year exercise intervention program for older adults in the Chicago area.

PROJECT COORDINATOR | DePaul University | 2015-2016

Assists in recruitment strategies & focus group procedures. Running participants in lab experiments.

Data entry & analysis. Helped coordinate the 2016

Annual Association for Psychological Science

Pre-Conference.

**DISSERTATION ASSISTANT** | DePaul University | 2015-2016 Primary responsibilities: developing guidelines for coding procedures, transcribing interviews, identifying themes in data/thematic analyses.

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | DePaul University | 2014-2015

Actively work through the phases of empirical study with research team. Compose literature reviews examining gender differences in workplace interactions. UG Thesis: Influence of virtual versus face-to-face interactions on negotiation outcomes.

#### COURSEWORK

Industrial-Organizational Psychology

Organizational Behavior

Community Psychology

Developmental Psychology

Social Psychology

Research Methods (I-III)

Statistics / Data Analytics (I-IV)

Psychological Measurement

Advanced Psychometrics

Neuroeconomics

Consumer Behavior

Theories in Judgment & Decision Making

Theories in Learning & Cognition

Abnormal Psychology

Physiological Psychology

Human Anatomy & Pathophysiology

Cognitive Neuroscience

Systems in Neurobiology

Sociolinguistics

Critical Thinking/Logic

Political Philosophy

Comparative Literature

Human-Computer Interaction

Computer Science Fundamentals

Database Design & Development

Data Structures & Algorithms

Scripting for Interactive Systems

## AWARDS & AFFILIATIONS

2014-2016 International Honor Society in Psychology 2014-2016 Psychology Club, DePaul University 2014-2016 National Society of Collegiate Scholars

2015-2017 APS, Student & Professional Affiliate

2015-2017 AAAS, Student & Professional Affiliate

DCDM Merit Scholarship, CDM, DePaul University Excellence in Academic Achievement, CSH, DePaul University Latino/a Academic Excellence Award, CSH, DePaul University Adult Student Affairs Merit Scholarship, CSH, DePaul University Dean's List, DePaul University \*every quarter\*

## **EDUCATION**

DEFERRED

THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO | MSc

Graham School, Bioinformatics

2017-2018

**DEPAUL UNIVERSITY | MS** 

College of Computing & Digital Media

Human-Computer Interaction

2014 - 2016

**DEPAUL UNIVERSITY** | B.A.

College of Science & Health

**Psychology** 

GPA 3.9 | SUMMA CUM LAUDE

#### **CERTIFICATES**

AUG 2017- FEB 2018

NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY | GRADUATE CERTIFICATE

School of Professional Studies & McCormick School of Engineering Web Technologies

Including: Front-end & Back-end Web Development, UX/UI, User Research, Agile Project Management

\* To view an extensive, interactive list of all project work, please visit www.rynescarracypher.com

## PUBLICATIONS & CONFERENCES

Mikels, J., Young, N., Escarra-Cypher, K., Chen, A., Liu, X. & Stine-Morrow, E. (manuscript under revision/in review). Getting to the heart of the matter in later life: The central role of affect in health message framing for older individuals.

Brown, T.M., Grant, K.E., Keenan, K., Odeh, S., Escarra-Cypher, K., Katsonga-Phiri, T., Duffy, S. (under review). Examining the experiences of participants in a depression prevention program for preadolescent African American girls.

Co-organizer for the NIA sponsored 2016 Association for Psychological Sciences Pre-Conference entitled, Advancing Behavioral and Social Research on Aging, Chicago, Illinois